let's look at the solution to our
history predictor quiz in c a loop exits
at the beginning so the first loop will
do something like initialize i to zero
if i is equal to eight jump to done
otherwise do everything that is needed
for an iteration of the outer loop
and then branch back here
the inner loop will just do j equals
zero
and then if j is equal to 8
go to some label d1
do something
jump back here and the label d1 would
really be here
after which we are going like this
so how many entries do we need we need
at least one entry per branch although
in fact we need one entry for each
instruction but at least we need to have
entries for branches so we have a branch
that does this here we have a branch
that does this here we have a loopback
branch here and we have a loopback
branch here so we're talking about at
least four entries
in reality we need many many more in
order to do well on all four of these
branches we need to see what is the
longest history that any one of them
will have the pack branch is always
taken so really we don't even need a
history for it even a single two bit
counter will do well on these two but
this one we'll be testing eight times
for zero through seven
and stay in the loop and then the ninth
time it tests it jumps out so really it
has a pattern of length nine
which means we need an eight bit history
with an eighth bit history
we need two to the 8th
2-bit counters
so that leads to 256 2-bit counters now
what is the pattern of this branch here
it really is 8 times it's not taken
followed by a taken and that repeats
the inner branch does exactly the same
thing except it does it many more times
so if you look at how many possible
patterns we actually have
of length eight we have a pattern of
eight not takens
we have a pattern of seven not takens
followed by a taken we have a pattern of
six not taken then taken not taken etc
so we are really using only nine of
these two bit counters which again shows
that
a predictor of this type with a very
long history will waste a lot of its
many many entries